Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Literary File, 1841-1919, undated (Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37)
  - November Boughs, 1887; loc.04206; xxx.00460; xxx.00368; xxx.00352; xxx.00376; xxx.00369; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 30, Folder You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me (1887). Printed Copy.)
    Clipping from a newspaper of four Whitman poems: You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, 'Going Somewhere,' After the Supper and Talk, and Not Meagre Latent Boughs Alone. At the top is the title November Boughs. At the bottom of the clipping is written, in Whitman's hand, " 1887 ." The poems were published first in Lippincott's Magazine, November, 1887.
  - November Boughs, about 1887; loc.00326; xxx.00460; xxx.00368; xxx.00352; xxx.00376; xxx.00369; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 30, Folder You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me (1887). Proof Sheets.)
    Proof of a collection of four poems (You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, 'Going Somewhere,' After the Supper and Talk, and Not Meagre Latent Boughs Alone) under the general title November Boughs. This proof is made by pasting together proofs of each poem in the order desired.
  - November Boughs, about 1887; loc.02484; xxx.00460; xxx.00368; xxx.00352; xxx.00376; xxx.00369; poetry handwritten printed 1 leaf (Box 30, Folder You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me (1887). Proof Sheets.)
    Proofs of a collection of four poems (You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, 'Going Somewhere,' After the Supper and Talk, and Not Meagre Latent Boughs Alone) under the general title November Boughs.
  - [I was down in New Orleans], 1848–1849; loc.00353; xxx.00889; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 31, Folder ca. 1848–1849. "The People and John Quincy Adams")
    A corrected proof of The People and John Quincy Adams, which appeared in the New Orleans Daily Crescent while Whitman was editor of that newspaper in 1848–1849. No image of the verso is currently available.
  - [No poem sings], 1860–1876; loc.00920; xxx.00894; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 32, Folder 1860, "War Memoranda," draft)
    A heavily revised draft of Unnamed Remains the Bravest Soldier. This piece first appeared untitled in Memoranda During the War ( 1876 ). It was reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882 ).
  - [March & April, '63], 1863–1864; loc.00926; xxx.00846; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 32, Folder 1863, Mar.-Apr., "War Experiences," proof sheets with corrections)
    A corrected proof sheet detailing Whitman's work in hospitals during the Civil War. These paragraphs appeared in Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers. Visits Among Army Hospitals, At Washington, on the Field, and here in New-York New-York Times ( 11 December 1864 ).
  - ca. 1863, loc.00928; xxx.00896; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 32, Folder ca. 1863, "A Connecticut Case," New York Weekly Graphic, draft)
    A revised draft of A Connecticut Case, a piece of Civil War memoranda which was first included in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ) and later reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882.
  - 51st New York Veterans, 1864; loc.00929; xxx.00857; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 32, Folder 1864, Oct. 29, "Fifty-First New York Veterans," New York Times, Manuscript draft)
    A partial draft of Fifty-first New-York City Veterans, which appeared in the 29 October 1864 issue of the New-York Times. The verso of this draft includes snippets of prose, some of which Whitman included in various Civil War writings. The "Case of Catholic priest & altar &c at side of dying Irish boy" was included in Memoranda During the War ( 1876 ). The notes on female nurses during the war were used in Female Nurses for Soldiers, first published under the heading, A Few Words about Female Nurses for Soldiers, in The Soldiers, New-York Times ( 6 March 1865 ). This prose piece was reprinted in both Memoranda During the War ( 1876 ) and Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882 ).
  - The policy of the War Department in not exchanging prisoners, 1864; loc.00930; xxx.00897; xxx.00898; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 32, Folder ca. 1864, "The Policy of the War Department in Not Exchanging Prisoners")
    A short draft on the exchange of the prisoners of war, the last paragraph of which was revised and printed on 27 December 1864 in both The Prisoners New-York Times and What Stops the General Exchange of Prisoners of War?—Three-fourths of Our Men Already Exchanged by Death, or Mental and Bodily Ruin, and the Rest will Soon Follow Brooklyn Daily Eagle.
  - [Probably we can give no], about 1890; loc.05724; xxx.00589; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 35, Folder Prose."Personal and Old Age Memoranda" (Mar'91))
    Partial draft of the essay published as Some Personal and Old-Age Memoranda in the March 1891 issue of Lippincott's Monthly Magazine. The leaf is made from a proof copy of Autobiographic Note. From an old 'remembrance copy,' which had appeared in Horace Traubel's 1889 volume Camden's Compliment to Walt Whitman, to which is pasted an envelope addressed in the hand of Richard Maurice Bucke to Whitman. The essay was reprinted as Some Personal and Old-Age Jottings in the February 28, 1891 issue of The Critic, in Good-Bye My Fanc y ( 1891 ), and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [Here the aboriginal money circulated], about 1861; loc.00962; xxx.00913; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 35, Folder "Brooklyniana: History of Brooklyn and Long Island," drafts and notes)
    Notes on the "aboriginal money" Whitman identifies as the "Seawan, or Seawant." Whitman wrote about this currency in the fourth installment of Brooklyniana, which appeared in the 28 December 1861 issue of the Brooklyn Standard. For more on how this manuscript may have contributed to this piece of journalism, see Kimberly Winschel Banion, 'These terrible 30 or 40 hours': Washington at the Battle of Brooklyn in Whitman's 'The Sleepers' and 'Brooklyniana' Manuscripts, Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 27 ( Spring 2010 ), 193-212.
  - Hist Brooklyn, about 1862; loc.00963; xxx.00914; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 35, Folder "Brooklyniana: History of Brooklyn and Long Island," drafts and notes)
    There is no known connection between the recto of this manuscript—treating Washington's visit to Brooklyn in the 1790s—and Whitman's published work. The verso of this manuscript contains cancelled notes on the establishment of the Hudson Avenue Hospital in the mid-1840s. Whitman wrote about the Hudson Avenue Hospital in Brooklyniana. A Series of Local Articles, on Past and Present. No. 16, which appeared in the 29 March 1862 issue of the Brooklyn Standard. Though there are no direct textual links between the two, it is likely that these notes contributed to this piece of journalism.
  - [The first actual resident settlement], about 1861; loc.00980; xxx.00915; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 35, Folder "Brooklyniana: History of Brooklyn and Long Island," drafts and notes)
    Notes on the settlement of Brooklyn that may have contributed to the first installment of Brooklyniana; A Series of Local Articles, Past and Present. No. 1, first published in the Brooklyn Daily Standard on 3 June 1861.
  - Hendrik Hudson, 1855–1861; loc.00952; xxx.00971; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 35, Folder "Brooklyniana: History of Brooklyn and Long Island," drafts and notes)
    Notes on Hendrick Hudson that appear to have contributed to Brooklyniana: A Series of Local Articles, on Past and Present. No. 2, Daily Standard ( 5 June 1861 ).
  - [True, I could not construct], about 1882; loc.05856; xxx.00530; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Complete Human Identity," draft)
    A heavily revised, partial draft of A Memorandum at a Venture, first published in the June 1882 issue of North American Review.
  - [The North too will eliminate], about 1874; loc.00996; xxx.00915; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Eliminate Fanatics," draft)
    The recto includes two prose paragraphs that contributed to the first installment of 'Tis But Ten Years Since, which appeared in the New York Weekly Graphic in January 1874. The verso contains a fragment of correspondence.
  - [Many consider the expressions], 1884–1888; loc.01015; xxx.00410; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Expressions of Poetry," clipping with corrections)
    Two short clippings of Whitman's own prose, which have been pasted to a larger sheet and feature corrections in Whitman's hand. The printed text appeared uncorrected in the 5 January 1884 issue of the Critic with the title, A Backward Glance on My Own Road. This essay was revised and included in Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers ( 1888 ) before parts of it were combined with two other pieces of journalism (How I Made a Book, Philadelphia Press, 11 July 1886; My Book and I, Lippincott's Magazine, January 1887 ) and published as A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads in November Boughs ( 1888 ).
  - [The genuine miracles of Christ], about 1855; loc.01019; xxx.00115; xxx.00048; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "The Genuine Miracles of Christ," draft)
    A cancelled prose manuscript containing lines which contributed to Whitman's published poetry. The line which reads, "the vast elemental sympathy which, only the human soul is capable of generating and emitting in steady and limitless floods," was used, slightly revised, in A Song of Joys, which first appeared in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass, as Poem of Joys. The line which reads, "descend from the tips of his fingers from the smell of his body from the vapor of his lungs" was revised and used in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, and eventually was included in what ultimately came to be the 39th stanza of Song of Myself.
  - [I well remember Lafayette's laying], about 1862; loc.01027; xxx.00919; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Lafayette in Brooklyn," draft)
    Notes on the Apprentice's Library in Brooklyn. Whitman published a short history of the Apprentice's Library in Brooklyniana: A Series of Local Articles, on Past and Present No. 15., which first appeared in the issue of the Brooklyn Standard.
  - Entering a long farm-lane, about 1882; loc.01030; xxx.00920; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "A Long Farm-Lane," draft)
    A draft of Entering a Long Farm-Lane, which first appeared in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [mark the figure], about 1860; loc.01032; xxx.00115; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Mark the Figure," draft)
    Two scraps pasted together to make one leaf. Lines from this manuscript were revised and used in A Song of Joys, which first appeared in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass, as Poem of Joys.
  - A Book of "Contemporaneous Notes.", 1881; loc.01035; xxx.00923; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Notes on Richard M. Bucke's Book," draft)
    A draft notice describing Richard M. Bucke's plans to publish a book titled, Contemporaneous Notes of Walt Whitman. This notice appeared unsigned in the 2 November 1881 issue of the Boston Evening Transcript under the heading, Personal.
  - born expressers of itself, about 1882; loc.01050; xxx.00529; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Spirit of Transactions," draft)
    A partial draft of Poetry To-Day in America—Shakespere—The Future, which appeared in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [and a surplus of a hundred millions & more], 1891; loc.01055; xxx.00560; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 36, Folder Undated, "These States and the Kosmical Scale," draft)
    This manuscript is a partial draft of American National Literature. Is There Any Such Thing—or Can There Ever Be?, which first appeared in the March 1891 issue of North American Review under the title, Have We a National Literature? before appearing in Good-Bye By Fancy ( 1891, and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [curiously writes itself], about 1870; loc.01077; xxx.00746; poetry prose handwritten 3 leaves (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Twilight Whisperings," draft)
    These manuscript pages reflect Whitman's experiences visiting the sick in hospitals in Washington during "the Secession War." Two lines from this manuscript, "At vacancy with Nature / Acceptive and at ease," were used as part of the poem Whitman presents in, A Quintette, first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Twilight Whisperings, 1870–1882; loc.01078; xxx.00745; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Twilight Whisperings," draft)
    This manuscript contains notes for a potential poem or prose piece, with two possible titles Twilight Whisperings and Chants at Early Candle Light. The relationship of this note to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - [I lately heard a lady], 1841–1865; loc.01079; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 36, Folder Undated, "A Venetian Fable," draft)
    This prose manuscript comments on a "Venetian fable," which is possibly a piece of early fiction. The date and relationship of this manuscript to Whitman's published work are unknown.
  - [In considering the aims], 1855–1892; loc.01080; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Walt Whitman's Writings," draft)
    This manuscript contains a small newspaper clipping review of Leaves of Grass, along with Whitman's comments about himself as an artist. The word "Horace" is written on the verso.
  - What is Poetry?, 1841-1892; loc.01070; poetry handwritten 2 leaves (Box 36, Folder What is Poetry)
    Whitman has annotated, What is Poetry?, a holograph by George D. Prentice.
  - [Yet Alas! while how near], 1841-1892; loc.01072; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 36, Folder Whither are we Sailing?)
    Sections of paper are pasted together in this prose reflection on "the motif of life." The relationship of these revised drafts to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - [Which leads me to another point], about 1891; loc.01074; xxx.00591; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 36, Folder Undated, "The Whole Past Century," draft)
    In these prose notes, Whitman reflects on the impact of the Civil War on the nation. Written at the top of the page, in an unknown hand, possibly that of Horace Traubel, "see notes Mar 18 1891." This manuscript contributed to American's Bulk Average, which first appeared in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [Why should I be afraid], 1855-1892; loc.01075; xxx.00410; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 36, Folder Undated, "Why Should I Be Afraid?" draft)
    On the verso of what appears to be an incoming letter, Whitman states that he has "abandon'd the conventional themes." These comments were revised and published in A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads,, the essay that Whitman used to close the 1891–92 edition of Leaves of Grass. A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads first appeared in Lippincott's Magazine ( January 1887 ), under the title My Book and I. Reprinted in Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers ( 1888 ), My Book and I was also combined with How I Made a Book, Philadelphia Press ( 11 July 1889 ) and A Backward Glance on My Own Road, Critic ( 5 January 1884 ) and published as A Backward Glance in November Boughs ( 1888 ).
  - [Scoria], 1841-1892; loc.01065; poetry handwritten 5 leaves (Box 36, Folder Words for an Intended Dictionary)
    This list of English and foreign words and phrases, along with definitions, may have been sketches for a dictionary.
  - [floor with his hands in his pockets], 1841-1892; loc.01066; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 36, Folder Work on the Farm)
    This prose manuscript portrays a person in a farm scene. The relationship to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - [Some 35 years ago], 1876; loc.01076; xxx.00943; prose handwritten 6 leaves (Box 36, Folder 1876, Oct.2, "In Memory of Thomas Paine," signed draft)
    Dated " Oct 2 '76 " on the last page, this manuscript is a draft of Whitman's speech on Thomas Paine, which was first published in the New York Daily Tribune ( 29 January 1877 ) as Walt Whitman on Thomas Paine. This piece was later published in Specimen Days (1882–1883) as In Memory of Thomas Paine before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Lincoln, 1870–1874; loc.01760; xxx.00525; xxx.00915; prose 6 leaves handwritten printed (Box 37, Folder ca. 1878–1890, "Abraham Lincoln")
    Notes on Abraham Lincoln and the political climate leading up to the "attempted secession," including handwritten corrections of printed prose. This manuscript contributed to Origins of Attempted Secession. Not the whole matter, but some facts worth conning to-day and any day, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). Origins of Attempted Secession was first published as part of 'Tis But Ten Years Since [First Paper], New York Weekly Graphic ( 24 January 1874 ). Portions of this essay were revised and used in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–1876 ) before appearing in Specimen Days & Collect. Whitman included Origins of Attempted Secession in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [to speak a reverent word], 1879–1881; loc.01761; xxx.00531; prose 33 leaves handwritten printed (Box 37, Folder 1879, "Death of Abraham Lincoln," reading book with proofs, printed pages, and drafts)
    Manuscript notes and clippings of printed prose gathered by Whitman in a homemade notebook created from a copy of John Dunbar Hylton's, Bride of Gettysburg ( 1878 ). Whitman appears to have used this book as a notebook in preparation for his lecture, "Death of Abraham Lincoln." Portions of this speech were originally published as Abraham Lincoln's Death. Walt Whitman's Account of the Scene at Ford's Theatre, New York Sun ( 12 February 1876 ) and were included in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–1876 ). Abraham Lincoln's Death was revised and published as A Poet on the Platform, New York Daily Tribune ( 15 April 1879 ) and was subsequently reprinted as Death of Abraham Lincoln in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before finally appearing in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [The subject or text of my], 1879–1887; loc.01762; xxx.00531; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 37, Folder 1886, Apr. 15, "Abraham Lincoln")
    Manuscript notes attached to a scrap of printed prose, both of which relate to Whitman's Lincoln lecture, titled "Death of Abraham Lincoln." Whitman published this address in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before including it in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [for closing passage], 1875–1886; loc.01799; xxx.00479; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 37, Folder ca. 1877–1883, Death of Abraham Lincoln, notes)
    A heavily revised prose manuscript in which Whitman worked through ideas on the death of Abraham Lincoln. Whitman himself scrawled "Death of Abraham Lincoln" at the top of this manuscript; however, no other textual link can be made between this manuscript and Death of Abraham Lincoln. This manuscript appears to be a draft of another prose piece on Lincoln, titled Abraham Lincoln. This essay was first published, untitled, in Allen Thorndike Rice, ed., Reminiscences of Abraham Lincoln ( 1886 ). Whitman reprinted this essay in November Boughs ( 1888 ). A revised version of the essay appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [for Abraham Lincoln], 1877–1886; loc.01800; xxx.00479; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 37, Folder ca. 1877–1883, 'Death of Abraham Lincoln,' notes)
    Notes toward a draft of Abraham Lincoln, first published, untitled, in Allen Thorndike Rice, ed., Reminiscences of Abraham Lincoln ( 1886 ). Whitman reprinted this essay in November Boughs ( 1888 ). A revised version of the essay appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman composed these notes on a piece of incoming correspondence.
- Notes and Notebooks, 1847-91, undated (Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42)
  This series includes notebooks and handmade booklets created from pages tied or pasted together. These items contain Whitman's thoughts and ideas, either personal or literary, including trial lines and titles for poems, draft fragments, clippings, and names and addresses. In addition, the series contains reference notes and synopses of Whitman's studies on human rights, slavery, religion, philology, language and grammar, and classical studies. The materials are arranged chronologically.
  The notes held in this series are unbound items arranged by the following topics: addresses and names, Brooklyniana, literary notes, miscellany, personal notes, printing and publishing notes, and reference notes.
  - Talk with Mr. Hartshorn, 1855-1861; loc.07017; xxx.01000; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 38, Folder Notes 1847–1891, Brooklyniana, undated, Guy's picture of Brooklyn)
    These notes discuss the authenticity of a painting by Francis Guy. Whitman wrote about Guy and one of his paintings in the third installment of the Brooklyniana series, which first appeared in the Brooklyn Daily Standard on 12 June 1861.
  - [George Walker], between 1855-1856; loc.00143; xxx.00116; xxx.00112; xxx.00052; xxx.00047; xxx.00119; xxx.00221; xxx.00110; xxx.00015; xxx.00053; poetry prose about 45 leaves handwritten (Box 37, Folder 1855-1856, Crossing Brooklyn Ferry trial lines)
    A notebook Whitman used for various purposes in the mid-1850s. Edward F. Grier, in his edition of Whitman's Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts, 6 vols. (New York: New York University Press, 1984), 1:226–243, noted that the notebook contains lines and phrases that relate to several poems: Song of the Broad-Axe, Crossing Brooklyn Ferry, I Sing the Body Electric, Starting from Paumanok, A Song for Occupations, By Blue Ontario's Shore, Salut au Monde!, To One Shortly to Die, and A Woman Waits for Me.
  - [the scope of government], between 1855-1856; loc.00157; xxx.00009; xxx.00229; poetry prose about 20 leaves handwritten (Box 37, Folder 1855-1856 (?), Government, Nature, Trial Lines, Self-Advice)
    A notebook Whitman used for various purposes in the mid-1850s. Edward F. Grier, in his edition of Whitman's Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (New York: New York University Press, 1984. 6 vols.), noted that the notebook contains lines and phrases that relate to several poems: Assurances, This Compost, and an unfinished poem entitled The Insects. On some of the leaves Whitman has rotated the notebook and written upside down.
  - [(illeg.) Dick Hunt], 1856-1857; loc.00028; xxx.00116; xxx.00261; xxx.00239; xxx.00047; xxx.00084; xxx.00241; xxx.00064; xxx.00035; xxx.00120; xxx.00136; xxx.00109; xxx.00129; poetry prose about 90 leaves handwritten (Box 38, Folder 1857 Trial Lines and Descriptions)
    A notebook Whitman used for various purposes in the mid-1850s. Edward F. Grier, in his edition of Whitman's Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts, 6 vols. (New York: New York University Press, 1984 ), 1: 246–280, noted that the notebook contains lines and phrases that relate to several poems: Song of the Broad-Axe, To a Common Prostitute, You Felons on Trial in Courts, Starting from Paumanok, Trickle Drops, I Was Looking for a Long While, Poem of Joys, Facing West from California's Shores, To the States, A Song of the Rolling Earth, On the Beach a Night Alone, Full of Life Now, and With Antecedents.
  - [In his presence], 1850–1871; loc.00483; xxx.00264; prose poetry 14 leaves handwritten